<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="mvctutorial1" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">
  <chapterinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Ian</firstname>

      <surname>MacLennan</surname>
    </author>

    <date>January 30, 2007</date>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Developing a Model-View-Controller Component - Part 1</title>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial1.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The new framework in Joomla! 1.5 unleashes a great deal of power for
    developers. The code has been completely overhauled and cleaned up. This
    tutorial will guide you through the process of developing a component
    using this new framework.</para>

    <para>The scope of this project will be to develop a simple Hello World!
    component. In future tutorials, this simple framework will be built upon
    to show the full power and versatility of the MVC design pattern in
    Joomla!</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial1.requirements">
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>You need Joomla! 1.5 or greater for this tutorial.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial1.mvcintroduction">
    <title>Introduction to Model-View-Controller</title>

    <para>While the idea behind a component may seem extremely simple, code
    can quickly become very complex as additional features are added or the
    interface is customized.</para>

    <para>Model-View-Controller (herein referred to as MVC) is a software
    design pattern that can be used to organize code in such a way that the
    business logic and data presentation are separate. The premise behind this
    approach is that if the business logic is grouped into one section, then
    the interface and user interaction that surrounds the data can revised and
    customized without having to reprogram the business logic.</para>

    <para>There are three main parts of an MVC component. They are described
    here in brief, but for a more thorough explanation, please refer to the
    links provided at the end of this tutorial.</para>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial1.mvcintroduction.model">
      <title>Model</title>

      <para>The model is the part of the component that encapsulates the
      application's data. It will often provide routines to manage and
      manipulate this data in a meaningful way in addition to routines that
      retrieve the data from the model. In our case, the model will contain
      methods to add, remove and update information about the greetings in the
      database. It will also contain methods to retrieve the list of greetings
      from the database. In general, the underlying data access technique
      should be encapsulated in the model. In this way, if an application is
      to be moved from a system that utilizes a flat file to store its
      information to a system that uses a database, the model is the only
      element that needs to be changed, not the view or the controller.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial1.mvcintroduction.view">
      <title>View</title>

      <para>The view is the part of the component that is used to render the
      data from the model in a manner that is suitable for interaction. For a
      web-based application, the view would generally be an HTML page that is
      returned to the data. The view pulls data from the model (which is
      passed to it from the controller) and feeds the data into a template
      which is populated and presented to the user. The view does not cause
      the data to be modified in any way, it only displays data retrieved from
      the model.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial1.mvcintroduction.controller">
      <title>Controller</title>

      <para>The controller is responsible for responding to user actions. In
      the case of a web application, a user action is (generally) a page
      request. The controller will determine what request is being made by the
      user and respond appropriately by triggering the model to manipulate the
      data appropriately and passing the model into the view. The controller
      does not display the data in the model, it only triggers methods in the
      model which modify the data, and then pass the model into the view which
      displays the data.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial1.mvcimplementation">
    <title>Joomla! MVC Implementation</title>

    <para>In Joomla!, the MVC pattern is implemented using three classes:
    <classname>JModel</classname>, <classname>JView</classname> and
    <classname>JController</classname>. For more detailed information about
    these classes, please refer to the API reference documentation
    (WIP).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial1.creatingcomponent">
    <title>Creating a Component</title>

    <para>For our basic component, we only require five files:<simplelist>
        <member><filename>hello.php</filename> - this is the entry point to
        our component</member>

        <member><filename>controller.php</filename> - this file contains our
        base controller</member>

        <member><filename>views/hello/view.html.php</filename> - this file
        retrieves the necessary data and pushes it into the template</member>

        <member><filename>views/hello/tmpl/default.php</filename> - this is
        the template for our output</member>

        <member><filename>hello.xml</filename> - this is an XML file that
        tells Joomla! how to install our component.</member>
      </simplelist></para>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial1.creatingcomponent.entrypoint">
      <title>Creating the Entry Point</title>

      <para>Joomla! is always accessed through a single point of entry:
      <filename>index.php</filename> for the Site Application or
      <filename>administrator/index.php</filename> for the Administrator
      Application. The application will then load the required component,
      based on the value of 'option' in the URL or in the POST data. For our
      component, the URL would be:</para>

      <para>
        <code>index.php?option=com_hello&amp;view=hello</code>
      </para>

      <para>This will load our main file, which can be seen as the single
      point of entry for our component:
      <filename>components/com_hello/hello.php</filename>.</para>

      <para>The code for this file is fairly typical across components.</para>

      <xi:include href="code/site_hello.php.xml" />

      <para>The first statement is a security check.</para>

      <para>JPATH_COMPONENT is the absolute path to the current component, in
      our case components/com_hello. If you specifically need either the Site
      component or the Administrator component, you can use
      JPATH_COMPONENT_SITE or JPATH_COMPONENT_ADMINISTRATOR.</para>

      <para>DS is the directory separator of your system: either '/' or '\'.
      This is automatically set by the framework so the developer doesn't have
      to worry about developing different versions for different server OSs.
      DS should always be used when referring to files on the local
      server.</para>

      <para>After loading the base controller, we check if a specific
      controller is needed. In this component, the base controller is the only
      controller, but we will leave this here for future use.</para>

      <para><classname>JRequest</classname>:getVar() finds a variable in the
      URL or the POST data. So if our URL is
      index.php?option=com_hello&gt;controller=controller_name, then we can
      retrieve our controller name in our component using: echo
      <classname>JRequest</classname>::getVar('controller');</para>

      <para>Now we have our base controller
      '<classname>HelloController</classname>' in com_hello/controller.php,
      and, if needed, additional controllers like
      '<classname>HelloControllerController1</classname>' in
      com_hello/controllers/controller1.php. Using this standard naming scheme
      will make things easy later on:
      '{Componentname}{Controller}{Controllername}'</para>

      <para>After the controller is created, we instruct the controller to
      execute the task, as defined in the URL:
      index.php?option=com_hello&amp;task=sometask. If no task is set, the
      default task 'display' will be assumed. When display is used, the 'view'
      variable will decide what will be displayed. Other common tasks are
      save, edit, new...</para>

      <para>The controller might decide to redirect the page, usually after a
      task like 'save' has been completed. This last statement takes care of
      the actual redirection.</para>

      <para>The main entry point (hello.php) essentially passes control to the
      controller, which handles performing the task that was specified in the
      request.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial1.creatingcomponent.creatingcontroller">
      <title>Creating the Controller</title>

      <para>Our component only has one task - greet the world. Therefore, the
      controller will be very simple. No data manipulation is required. All
      that needs to be done is the appropriate view loaded. We will have only
      one method in our controller: display(). Most of the required
      functionality is built into the JController class, so all that we need
      to do is invoke the JController::display() method.</para>

      <para>The code for the base controller is:</para>

      <xi:include href="code/site_controller.php.xml" />

      <para>The <classname>JController</classname> constructor will always
      register a display() task and unless otherwise specified (using the
      registerDefaultTask() method), it will set it as the default
      task.</para>

      <para>This barebones display() method isn't really even necessary since
      all it does is invoke the parent constructor. However, it is a good
      visual clue to indicate what is happening in the controller.</para>

      <para>The <classname>JController</classname>::display() method will
      determine the name of the view and layout from the request and load that
      view and set the layout. When you create a menu item for your component,
      the menu manager will allow the administrator to select the view that
      they would like the menu link to display and to specify the layout. A
      view usually refers to a view of a certain set of data (i.e. a list of
      cars, a list of events, a single car, a single event). A layout is a way
      that that view is organized.</para>

      <para>In our component, we will have a single view called hello, and a
      single layout (default).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial1.creatingcomponent.creatingview">
      <title>Creating the View</title>

      <para>The task of the view is very simple: It retrieves the data to be
      displayed and pushes it into the template. Data is pushed into the
      template using the <classname>JView</classname>::assignRef
      method.</para>

      <para>The code for the view is:</para>

      <xi:include href="code/site_views_hello_view.html.php.xml" />
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial1.creatingcomponent.creatingtemplate">
      <title>Creating the Template</title>

      <para>Joomla! templates/layouts are regular PHP files that are used to
      layout the data from the view in a particular manner. The variables
      assigned by the JView::assignRef method can be accessed from the
      template using $this-&gt;{propertyname} (see the template code below for
      an example).</para>

      <para>Our template is very simple: we only want to display the greeting
      that was passed in from the view:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?php // no direct access
defined('_JEXEC') or die('Restricted access'); ?&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;?php echo $this-&gt;greeting; ?&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial1.creatingcomponent.wrappingitup">
      <title>Wrapping It All Up - Creating the hello.xml File</title>

      <para>It is possible to install a component manually by copying the
      files using an FTP client and modifying the database tables. It is more
      efficient to create a package file that will allow the Joomla! Installer
      to do this for you. This package file contains a variety of
      information:<simplelist>
          <member>basic descriptive details about your component (i.e. name),
          and optionally, a description, copyright and license
          information.</member>

          <member>a list of files that need to be copied.</member>

          <member>optionally, a PHP file that performs additional install and
          uninstall operations.</member>

          <member>optionally, an SQL file which contains database queries that
          should be executed upon install/uninstall</member>
        </simplelist></para>

      <para>The format of the XML file is as follows:</para>

      <xi:include href="code/hello.xml.xml" />

      <para>If you look closely you will notice that there are some files that
      will be copied that we have not discussed. These are the
      <filename>index.html</filename> files. An
      <filename>index.html</filename> file is placed in each directory to
      prevent prying users from getting a directory listing. If there is no
      <filename>index.html</filename> file, some web servers will list the
      directory contents. This is often undesirable. These files have the
      simple line:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;html&gt;&lt;body bgcolor="#FFFFFF"&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>It will simply display a blank page.</para>

      <para>The other file is the <filename>admin.hello.php</filename> file.
      This is the entry point for the admin section of our component. Since we
      don't have an admin section of our component, it will have the same
      content as the <filename>index.html</filename> files at this point in
      time.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial1.contributors">
    <title>Contributors</title>

    <simplelist>
      <member>mjaz</member>

      <member>staalanden</member>
    </simplelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial1.download">
    <title>Download</title>

    <para>The component can be downloaded at: <ulink
    url="packages/com_hello1.zip">com_hello1.zip</ulink></para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>