<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="databasetutorial">
  <chapterinfo>
    <author>
      <surname>Louis Landry</surname>
    </author>

    <date>May 19, 2007</date>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Using the 1.5 Database Libraries</title>

  <sect1 id="databasetutorial.getobject">
    <title>Getting a database object</title>

    <para>This tutorial should provide you with the basics of what you need to
    know to use the Joomla! database libraries.</para>

    <sect2 id="databasetutorial.getobject.system">
      <title>Get the system database object</title>

      <para>The easiest way to get a database object is by getting the system
      database object returned by the JFactory class. The static method
      JFactory::getDBO() returns a singleton instance of the system database
      object regardless of scope and is the recommended way of getting this
      object.</para>

      <programlisting>// This gets the database object using the JFactory class
$db = &amp;JFactory::getDBO();</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="databasetutorial.getobject.custom">
      <title>Creating a custom database object</title>

      <para>Joomla! 1.5 introduces the concept of database drivers which will
      allow you to get database objects that point to different database
      sources.</para>

      <programlisting>// Create a new database object
$myDB = new JDatabase::getInstance( $options );</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="databasetutorial.usage">
    <title>Using the database object</title>

    <para>For the purposes of this tutorial we will use a very simple database
    table that stores information about dogs. The database table has a dog_id
    field with a unique integer id field, a name field and a color field for
    each dog. To keep things simple we have only added three dogs to our
    database table:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Dog 1 is named Spot and is white.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Dog 2 is named Fido and is brown.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Dog 3 is named Buster and is also brown.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The following table represents our database table which we will
    simply call, dogs.</para>

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">dog_id</entry>

            <entry align="center">name</entry>

            <entry align="center">color</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>1</entry>

            <entry>Spot</entry>

            <entry>white</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>2</entry>

            <entry>Fido</entry>

            <entry>brown</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>3</entry>

            <entry>Buster</entry>

            <entry>brown</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    <sect2 id="databasetutorial.usage.singlefield">
      <title>Select one field from one row</title>

      <para>Lets say for example that I want to find out the name of the
      second dog in my database table. This is a fairly straightfoward task, I
      simply need to get the name value in the name field where the dog_id is
      2 so lets build an SQL query to do that.</para>

      <programlisting>SELECT name FROM dogs WHERE dog_id = 2</programlisting>

      <para>Easy enough, now we need to actually get the value using our
      database object.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>First we need to get ourselves a database object that is
          connected to the database our dogs table is in.</para>

          <programlisting>// Get the system database object.
$db = &amp;JFactory::getDBO();</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Next we need to set our query to the database object. To do
          this we will use the setQuery method.</para>

          <programlisting>// Set our query to the database object.
$db-&gt;setQuery( 'SELECT name FROM dogs WHERE dog_id = 2' );</programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Lastly we call the loadResult() method.</para>

          <programlisting>// Use the loadResult() method to get only the first value from the first row of the result set.
$name = $db-&gt;loadResult();</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>