<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="helloworldmodule" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">
  <chapterinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Ian</firstname>

      <surname>MacLennan</surname>
    </author>

    <date>March 3, 2007</date>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Creating a Hello World Module for Joomla! 1.5</title>

  <para>A module is a lightweight and flexible extension that is used for page
  rendering. They are used for small bits of the page that are generally less
  complex and are able to be seen across different components.</para>

  <para>You can see many examples of modules in the standard Joomla! install:
  - menus - Latest News - Login form - and many more.</para>

  <para>This tutorial will explain how to go about creating a simple Hello
  World module. Through this tutorial you will learn the basic file structure
  of a module. This basic structure can then be expanded to produce more
  elaborate modules.</para>

  <sect1 id="helloworldmodule.filestructure">
    <title>File Structure</title>

    <para>There are four basic files that are used in the standard pattern of
    module development:<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>mod_helloworld.php - This file is the main entry point for the
          module. It will perform any necessary initialization routines, call
          helper routines to collect any necessary data, and include the
          template which will display the module output.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>mod_helloworld.xml - This file contains information about the
          module. It defines the files that need to be installed by the
          Joomla! installer and specifies configuration parameters for the
          module.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>helper.php - This file contains the helper class which is used
          to do the actual work in retrieving the information to be displayed
          in the module (usually from the database or some other
          source).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>tmpl/default.php - This is the module template. This file will
          take the data collected by mod_helloworld.php and generate the HTML
          to be displayed on the page.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="helloworldmodule.mod_helloworld">
    <title>Creating mod_helloworld.php</title>

    <para>The mod_helloworld.php file will perform three tasks: <itemizedlist
        mark="bullet">
        <listitem>include the helper.php file which contains the class to be
        used to collect the necessary data</listitem>

        <listitem>invoke the appropriate helper class method to retrieve the
        data</listitem>

        <listitem>include the template to display the output.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The helper class is defined in our helper.php file. This file is
    included with a require_once statement:</para>

    <programlisting>require_once( dirname(__FILE__).DS.'helper.php' );</programlisting>

    <para>require_once is used because our helper functions are defined within
    a class, and we only want the class defined once.</para>

    <para>Our helper class has not been defined yet, but when it is, it will
    contain one method: getHello(). For our basic example, it is not really
    necessary to do this - the “Hello, World” message that this method returns
    could simply be included in the template. We use a helper class here to
    demonstrate this basic technique.</para>

    <para>Our module currently does not use any parameters, but we will pass
    them to the helper method anyway so that it can be used later if we decide
    to expand the functionality of our module.</para>

    <para>The helper class method is invoked in the following way:</para>

    <programlisting>$hello = modHelloWorldHelper::getHello( $params );</programlisting>

    <sect2 id="helloworldmodule.mod_helloworld.completedmodhelloworld">
      <title>Completed mod_helloworld.php file</title>

      <para>The complete mod_helloworld.php file is as follows:</para>

      <xi:include href="code/mod_helloworld.php.xml" />

      <para>The one line that we haven’t explained so far is the first line.
      This line checks to make sure that this file is being included from the
      Joomla! application. This is necessary to prevent variable injection and
      other potential security concerns.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="helloworldmodule.helper">
    <title>Creating helper.php</title>

    <para>The helper.php file contains that helper class that is used to
    retrieve the data to be displayed in the module output. As stated earlier,
    our helper class will have one method: getHello(). This method will return
    the ‘Hello, World’ message.</para>

    <para>Here is the code for the helper.php file:</para>

    <xi:include href="code/helper.php.xml" />

    <para>There is no rule stating that we must name our helper class as we
    have, but it is helpful to do this so that it is easily identifiable and
    locateable.</para>

    <para>More advanced modules might include database requests or other
    functionality in the helper class method.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="helloworldmodule.template">
    <title>Creating tmpl/default.php</title>

    <para>The default.php file is the template which displays the module
    output.</para>

    <para>The code for the default.php file is as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;?php // no direct access
defined( '_JEXEC' ) or die( 'Restricted access' ); ?&gt;
&lt;?php echo $hello; ?&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>An important point to note is that the template file has the same
    scope as the mod_helloworld.php file. What this means is that the variable
    $hello can be defined in the mod_helloworld.php file and then used in the
    $hello file without any extra declarations or function calls.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="helloworldmodule.manifest">
    <title>Creating mod_helloworld.xml</title>

    <para>The mod_helloworld.xml is used to specify which files the installer
    needs to copy and is used by the Module Manager to determine which
    parameters are used to configure the module. Other information about the
    module is also specified in this file.</para>

    <para>The code for mod_helloworld.xml is as follows:</para>

    <xi:include href="code/mod_helloworld.xml.xml" />

    <para>You will notice that there are two additional files that we have not
    yet mentioned: index.html and tmpl/index.html. These files are included so
    that these directories cannot be browsed. If a used attempts to point
    their browser to these folders, the index.html file will be displayed.
    These files can be left empty or can contain the simple line:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;html&gt;&lt;body bgcolor="#FFFFFF"&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>which will display an empty page.</para>

    <para>Since our module does not use any parameters, this section is
    empty.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="helloworldmodule.conclusion">
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>Module development for Joomla! is a fairly simple, straightforward
    process. Using the techniques described in this tutorial, an endless
    variety of modules can be developed with little hassle.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>