<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" id="mvctutorial4">
  <chapterinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Ian</firstname>

      <surname>MacLennan</surname>
    </author>

    <date>March 9, 2007</date>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Developing a Model-View-Controller Component - Part 4 - Creating an
  Administrator Interface</title>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial4.introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>In the first three tutorials, we have developed a MVC component that
    retrieves its data from a table in the database. Currently, there is no
    way to add data to the database except to do it manually using another
    tool. In this tutorial, we will develop an administrator section for our
    component which will make it possible to manage the entries in the
    database.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial4.creatingframework">
    <title>Creating the Basic Framework</title>

    <para>The basic framework of the administrator panel is very similar to
    the site portion. The main entry point for the administrator section of
    the component is admin.hello.php. This file is identical to the hello.php
    file that was used in the site portion except the name of the controller
    it loads will be changed to HellosController. The default controller is
    also called controller.php and this file is identical to the default
    controller in the site portion, with the exception that the controller is
    named HellosController instead of HelloController. This difference is so
    that JController will by default load the hellos view, which will display
    a list of our greetings.</para>

    <para>Here is the listing for admin.hello.php:</para>

    <programlisting xml:base="code/admin_admin.hello.php.xml">    &lt;?php
/**
 * @package    Joomla.Tutorials
 * @subpackage Components
 * @link http://dev.joomla.org/component/option,com_jd-wiki/Itemid,31/id,tutorials:components/
 * @license    GNU/GPL
*/

// no direct access

defined( '_JEXEC' ) or die( 'Restricted access' );

// Require the base controller

require_once( JPATH_COMPONENT.DS.'controller.php' );

// Require specific controller if requested
if($controller = JRequest::getVar( 'controller' )) {
    require_once( JPATH_COMPONENT.DS.'controllers'.DS.$controller.'.php' );
}

// Create the controller
$classname    = 'HellosController'.$controller;
$controller   = new $classname( );

// Perform the Request task
$controller-&gt;execute( JRequest::getVar( 'task' ) );

// Redirect if set by the controller
$controller-&gt;redirect();

?&gt;</programlisting>
    <para>The view and model that we will start with is the hellos view and
    the hellos model. We will start with the model.</para>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.creatingframework.hellosmodel">
      <title>The Hellos Model</title>

      <para>The Hellos Model will be very simple. The only operation that we
      currently need is the ability to retrieve the list of hellos from the
      database. This operation will be implemented in a method called
      getData().</para>

      <para>The JModel class has a built in protected method called
      _getList(). This method can be used to simplify the task of retrieving a
      list of records from the database. We simply need to pass it the query
      and it will return the list of records.</para>

      <para>At a later point in time, we might want to use our query from
      within another method. Therefore, we will create a private method called
      _buildQuery() which will return the query that will be passed to
      _getList(). This makes it easier to change the query as well since it is
      localized in one place.</para>

      <para>Therefore we need two methods in our class: getData() and
      _buildQuery().</para>

      <para>_buildQuery() simply returns the query. It looks like:</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * Returns the query
 * @return string The query to be used to retrieve the rows from the database
 */
function _buildQuery()
{
    $query = ' SELECT * '
           . ' FROM #__hello '
    ;

    return $query;
}</programlisting>
      <para>getData() will obtain the query and retrieve the records from the
      database. Now it might happen that we need to retrieve this list of data
      twice in one page load. It would be a waste to have to query the
      database twice. Therefore, we will have this method store the data in a
      protected property so that on subsequent requests it can simply return
      the data it has already retrieved. This property will be called
      _data.</para>

      <para>Here is the getData() method:</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * Retrieves the hello data
 * @return array Array of objects containing the data from the database
 */
function getData()
{
    // Lets load the data if it doesn't already exist
    if (empty( $this-&gt;_data ))
    {
        $query = $this-&gt;_buildQuery();
        $this-&gt;_data = $this-&gt;_getList( $query );
    }

    return $this-&gt;_data;
}</programlisting>
      <para>The completed model looks like:</para>

      <programlisting xml:base="code/admin_models_hellos.php.xml">    &lt;?php
/**
 * Hellos Model for Hello World Component
 * 
 * @package    Joomla.Tutorials
 * @subpackage Components
 * @link http://dev.joomla.org/component/option,com_jd-wiki/Itemid,31/id,tutorials:components/
 * @license        GNU/GPL
 */

// Check to ensure this file is included in Joomla!
defined('_JEXEC') or die();

jimport( 'joomla.application.component.model' );

/**
 * Hello Model
 *
 * @package    Joomla.Tutorials
 * @subpackage Components
 */
class HellosModelHellos extends JModel
{
    /**
     * Hellos data array
     *
     * @var array
     */
    var $_data;

    /**
     * Returns the query
     * @return string The query to be used to retrieve the rows from the database
     */
    function _buildQuery()
    {
        $query = ' SELECT * '
            . ' FROM #__hello '
        ;
        return $query;
    }

    /**
     * Retrieves the hello data
     * @return array Array of objects containing the data from the database
     */
    function getData()
    {
        // Lets load the data if it doesn't already exist
        if (empty( $this-&gt;_data ))
        {
            $query = $this-&gt;_buildQuery();
            $this-&gt;_data = $this-&gt;_getList( $query );
        }

        return $this-&gt;_data;
    }
}</programlisting>
      <para>This file is saved as models/hellos.php.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.creatingframework.hellosview">
      <title>The Hellos View</title>

      <para>Now that we have a model to retrieve our data, we need to display
      it. This view will be fairly similar to the view from the site section
      as well.</para>

      <para>Just as our model was automatically instantiated in the site, so
      it is in the administrator. Methods that start with get in the model can
      be accessed using the get() method of the JView class. So our view has
      three lines: one to retrieve the data from the model, one to push the
      data into the template, and one to invoke the display method to display
      the output. Thus we have:</para>

      <programlisting xml:base="code/admin_views_hellos_view.html.php.xml">    &lt;?php
/**
 * Hellos View for Hello World Component
 * 
 * @package    Joomla.Tutorials
 * @subpackage Components
 * @link http://dev.joomla.org/component/option,com_jd-wiki/Itemid,31/id,tutorials:components/
 * @license        GNU/GPL
 */

// Check to ensure this file is included in Joomla!
defined('_JEXEC') or die();

jimport( 'joomla.application.component.view' );

/**
 * Hellos View
 *
 * @package    Joomla.Tutorials
 * @subpackage Components
 */
class HellosViewHellos extends JView
{
    /**
     * Hellos view display method
     * @return void
     **/
    function display($tpl = null)
    {
        JToolBarHelper::title(   JText::_( 'Hello Manager' ), 'generic.png' );
        JToolBarHelper::deleteList();
        JToolBarHelper::editListX();
        JToolBarHelper::addNewX();

        // Get data from the model
        $items        = &gt; $this-&gt;get( 'Data');

        $this-&gt;assignRef('items',        $items);

        parent::display($tpl);
    }
}</programlisting>
      <para>This file is saved as
      <filename>views/hellos/view.html.php</filename>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.creatingframework.hellostemplate">
      <title>The Hellos Template</title>

      <para>The template will take the data pushed into it from the view and
      produce the output. We will display our output in a simple table. While
      the frontend template was very simple, in the administrator we will need
      a minimal amount of extra logic to handle looping through the
      data.</para>

      <para>Here is our template:</para>

      <programlisting xml:base="code/admin_views_hellos_tmpl_default.php.xml">    &lt;?php defined('_JEXEC') or die('Restricted access'); ?&gt;
&lt;form action="index.php" method="post" name="adminForm"&gt;
&lt;div id="editcell"&gt;
    &lt;table class="adminlist"&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th width="5"&gt;
                &lt;?php echo JText::_( 'ID' ); ?&gt;
            &lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;
                &lt;?php echo JText::_( 'Greeting' ); ?&gt;
            &lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;            
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;?php
    $k = 0;
    for ($i=0, $n=count( $this-&gt;items ); $i &lt; $n; $i++)
    {
        $row = &gt;$this-&gt;items[$i];
        ?&gt;
        &lt;tr class="&lt;?php echo "row$k"; ?&gt;"&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;
                &lt;?php echo $row-&gt;id; ?&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;
                &lt;?php echo $row-&gt;greeting; ?&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;?php
        $k = 1 - $k;
    }
    ?&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;input type="hidden" name="option" value="com_hello" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="task" value="" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="boxchecked" value="0" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="controller" value="hello" /&gt;

&lt;/form&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>This template is saved as views/hellos/tmpl/default.php.</para>

      <para>You will notice that our output is enclosed in a form. Though this
      is not necessary now, it will be soon.</para>

      <para>We have now completed the basic part of the first view. We have
      added five files to the admin section of our component:<simplelist>
          <member>admin.hello.php</member>

          <member>controller.php</member>

          <member>models/hellos.php</member>

          <member>views/hellos/view.html.php</member>

          <member>views/hellos/tmpl/default.php</member>
        </simplelist></para>

      <para>You can now add these files to the XML install file and give it a
      try!</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial4.addingfunctionality">
    <title>Adding Functionality</title>

    <para>So far our administrator section is pretty useless. It doesn't
    really do anything - all it does is display the entries that we have in
    our database.</para>

    <para>In order to make it useful, we need to add some buttons and
    links.</para>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.addingfunctionality.toolbar">
      <title>The Toolbar</title>

      <para>You may have noticed the toolbar that appears at the top of other
      Joomla! component administrator panels. Our component needs one as well.
      Joomla! makes this very easy to do. We will add buttons Delete records,
      Edit records, and create New records. We will also add a title that will
      be displayed on our toolbar.</para>

      <para>This is done by adding code to the view. To add the buttons, we
      use static methods from the Joomla! JToolBarHelper class. The code looks
      like:</para>

      <programlisting>JToolBarHelper::title(   JText::_( 'Hello Manager' ), 'generic.png' );
JToolBarHelper::deleteList();
JToolBarHelper::editListX();
JToolBarHelper::addNewX();</programlisting>
      <para>These three methods will create the appropriate buttons. The
      deleteList() method can optionally take up to three parameters - the
      first parameter is a string to display to the user to confirm that they
      want to delete the records. The second is the task that should be sent
      with the query (the default is 'remove'), and the third is the text that
      should be displayed below the button.</para>

      <para>The editListX() and addNewX() methods can each take two optional
      parameters. The first is the task (which are by default edit and add,
      respectively), and the second is the text that should be displayed below
      the button.</para>

      <remark>*You may have noticed the use of the JText::_ method in the
      template before and here as well. This is a handy function that makes
      component translation much easier. The JText::_ method will look up the
      string in your component language file and return the translated string.
      If not translation is found, it will return the string that you passed
      it. If you want to translate your component into another language, all
      you have to do is create a language file that will map the strings
      within the '' to the translated version of the string.</remark>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.addingfunctionality.checkboxes">
      <title>Checkboxes and Links</title>

      <para>We now have buttons. Two of those buttons operate on existing
      records. But how do we know which records to operate on? We have to let
      the user tell us. To do this, we need to add checkboxes to our table so
      that the user can select certain records. This is done in our
      template.</para>

      <para>In order to the add the checkboxes, we need to add an extra column
      into our table. We will add the column in between the two that we
      already have.</para>

      <para>In the header of the column, we will add a checkbox which can be
      used to toggle all the boxes below it on or off:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;th width="20"&gt;
    &lt;input type="checkbox" name="toggle" value="" onclick="checkAll(&lt;?php echo count( $this-&gt;items ); ?&gt;);" /&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>The Javascript checkAll function is a function that is built into
      the Joomla! base Javascript package that provides the functionality that
      we want here.</para>

      <para>Now we need to add the checkboxes into the individual rows.
      Joomla!'s JHTML class has a method, JHTML::_(), which will generate our
      checkbox for us. We will add the following line to our loop:</para>

      <programlisting>$checked    = JHTML::_('grid.id',   $i, $row-&gt;id );</programlisting>
      <para>after the line:</para>

      <programlisting>$row = &gt;$this-&gt;items[$i];</programlisting>
      <para>Then we will add a cell in between the two that we already
      have:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;?php echo $checked; ?&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>It can be cumbersome to have to check the box that we want to edit
      and then move up and click the edit button. Therefore, we will add a
      link that it will go straight to the greeting's edit form. We will add
      the following line after the call to the JHTML::_() method to generate
      the link HTML:</para>

      <programlisting>$link = JRoute::_( 'index.php?option=com_hello&gt;controller=hello&gt;task=edit&gt;cid[]='. $row-&gt;id );</programlisting>
      <para>And we include the link in the cell showing the greeting text:
      </para>

      <programlisting>&lt;td&gt;
    &lt;a href="&lt;?php echo $link; ?&gt;"&gt;&lt;?php echo $row-&gt;greeting; ?&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>You will notice that this link points to the hello controller.
      This controller will handle the data manipulation of our
      greetings.</para>

      <para>If you recall from above, we had four hidden input fields at the
      bottom of our form. The first input field was named 'option'. This field
      is necessary so that we stay in our component. The second input field
      was task. This form property gets set when one of the buttons in the
      toolbar is clicked. A Javascript error will result and the buttons will
      not work if this input field is omitted. The third input field is the
      boxchecked field. This field keeps track of the number of boxes that are
      checked. The edit and delete buttons will check to ensure that this is
      greater than zero and will not allow the form to be submitted if it is
      not. The fourth input field is the controller field. This is used to
      specify that tasks fired from this form will be handled by the hello
      controller.</para>

      <para>Here is the code for the completed default.php file:</para>

      <programlisting xml:base="code/admin_views_hellos_tmpl_default.phpa.xml">    &lt;?php 
/**
 * Default admin hello view for Hello World Component
 * 
 * @package    Joomla.Tutorials
 * @subpackage Components
 * @link http://dev.joomla.org/component/option,com_jd-wiki/Itemid,31/id,tutorials:modules/
 * @license        GNU/GPL
 */

defined('_JEXEC') or die('Restricted access');

?&gt;

&lt;form action="index.php" method="post" name="adminForm"&gt;
&lt;div id="editcell"&gt;
    &lt;table class="adminlist"&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;th width="5"&gt;
                &lt;?php echo JText::_( 'ID' ); ?&gt;
            &lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th width="20"&gt;   &lt;!-- checkbox to check all items --&gt;
                &lt;input type="checkbox" name="toggle" value="" onclick="checkAll( &lt;?php echo count($this-&gt;items); ?&gt; );" /&gt; 
            &lt;/th&gt;
            &lt;th&gt;
                &lt;?php echo JText::_( 'Greeting' ); ?&gt;
            &lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;            
    &lt;/thead&gt;

    &lt;?php
    $k = 0;

    for ($i=0, $n=count( $this-&gt;items ); $i &lt; $n; $i++)
    {
        $row =&gt; $this-&gt;items[$i];
        $checked = JHTML::_('grid.id', $i, $row-&gt;id );     //get checkbox HTML
        // get link HTML to edit task for this greeting
        $link = JRoute::_( 'index.php?option=com_hello&gt;controller=hello&gt;task=edit&gt;cid[]='. $row-&gt;id );
    ?&gt;
        &lt;tr class="&lt;?php echo "row$k"; ?&gt;"&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;
                &lt;?php echo $row-&gt;id; ?&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;
                 &lt;?php echo $checked; ?&gt; 
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;
                &lt;a href="&lt;?php echo $link; ?&gt;"&gt;&lt;?php echo $row-&gt;greeting; ?&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;?php
        $k = 1 - $k;    //switch row class
    }
    ?&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="option" value="com_hello" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="task" value="" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="boxchecked" value="0" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="controller" value="hello" /&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>Our hellos view is now complete. You can try out the component now
      to see the results.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty">
    <title>Getting Down and Dirty: Doing the Real Work</title>

    <para>Now that the Hellos view is done, it is time to move to the Hello
    view and model. This is where the real work will get done.</para>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.hellocontroller">
      <title>The Hello Controller</title>

      <para>Our default controller just isn't going to cut it when it comes to
      doing work - all it is capable of doing is displaying views.</para>

      <para>We need to be able to handle the tasks that we are launching from
      the Hellos view: add, edit and remove.</para>

      <para>Add and edit are essentially the same task: they both display a
      form to the user that allows a greeting to be edited. The only
      difference is that new displays a blank form, and edit displays a form
      with data already in it. Since they are similar, we will map the add
      task onto the edit task handler. This is specified in our
      constructor:</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * constructor (registers additional tasks to methods)
 * @return void
 */
function __construct()
{
    parent::__construct();

    // Register Extra tasks
    $this-&gt;registerTask( 'add'  ,     'edit' );
}</programlisting>
      <para>The first parameter of JController::registerTask is the task to
      map, and the second is the method to map it to.</para>

      <para>We will start with handling the edit task. The controller's job is
      fairly simple for the edit task. All it has to do is specify the view
      and layout to load (the hello view and the form layout). We will also
      tell Joomla! to disable the mainmenu while we are editing our greeting.
      This prevents users from leaving unsaved records open.</para>

      <para>Our edit task handler looks like:</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * display the edit form
 * @return void
 */
function edit()
{
    JRequest::setVar( 'view', 'hello' );
    JRequest::setVar( 'layout', 'form'  );
    JRequest::setVar('hidemainmenu', 1);

    parent::display();
}</programlisting>    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.helloview">
      <title>The Hello View</title>

      <para>The Hello view will display a form which will allow the user to
      edit a greeting. The display method if the hello view has to do a few
      simple tasks:<simplelist>
          <member>retrieve the data from the model</member>

          <member>create the toolbar</member>

          <member>pass the data into the template</member>

          <member>invoke the display() method to render the template</member>
        </simplelist></para>

      <para>This becomes a bit more complicated because the one view handles
      both the edit and add tasks. In our toolbar we want the user to know
      what whether they are adding or editing, so we have to determine which
      task was fired.</para>

      <para>Since we are already retrieving the record that we want to display
      from the model, we can use this data to determine what task was fired.
      If the task was edit, then the id field of our record will have been
      set. If the task was new, then it will not have been set. This can be
      used to determine if we have a new record or an existing record.</para>

      <para>We will add two buttons to the toolbar: save and cancel. Though
      the functionality will be the same, we want to display different buttons
      depending on whether it is a new or existing record. If it is a new
      record, we will display cancel. If it already exists, we will display
      close.</para>

      <para>Thus our display method looks like this:</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * display method of Hello view
 * @return void
 **/
function display($tpl = null)
{
    //get the hello
    $hello        =&gt; $this-&gt;get('Data');
    $isNew        = ($hello-&gt;id &lt; 1);

    $text = $isNew ? JText::_( 'New' ) : JText::_( 'Edit' );
    JToolBarHelper::title(   JText::_( 'Hello' ).': &lt;small&gt;&lt;small&gt;[ ' . $text.' ]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;' );
    JToolBarHelper::save();
    if ($isNew)  {
        JToolBarHelper::cancel();
    } else {
        // for existing items the button is renamed `close`
        JToolBarHelper::cancel( 'cancel', 'Close' );
    }

    $this-&gt;assignRef('hello',        $hello);
    parent::display($tpl);
}</programlisting>    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.hellomodel">
      <title>The Hello Model</title>

      <para>Our view needs data. Therefore, we need to create a model to model
      a hello.</para>

      <para>Our model will have two properties: _id and _data. _id will hold
      the id of the greeting and data will hold the data.</para>

      <para>We will start with a constructor, which will attempt to retrieve
      the id from the query:</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * Constructor that retrieves the ID from the request
 *
 * @access    public
 * @return    void
 */
function __construct()
{
    parent::__construct();

    $array = JRequest::getVar('cid',  0, '', 'array');
    $this-&gt;setId((int)$array[0]);
}</programlisting>
      <para>The JRequest::getVar() method is used to retrieve data from the
      request. The first parameter is the name of the form variable. The
      second parameter is the default value to assign if there is no value
      found. The third parameter is the name of the hash to retrieve the value
      from (get, post, etc), and the last value is the data type that should
      be forced on the value.</para>

      <para>Our constructor will take the first value from the cid array and
      assign it to the id.</para>

      <para>Our setId() method can be used to set our id. Changing the id that
      our model points to will mean the id points to the wrong data.
      Therefore, when we set the id, we will clear the data property:</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * Method to set the hello identifier
 *
 * @access    public
 * @param    int Hello identifier
 * @return    void
 */
function setId($id)
{
    // Set id and wipe data
    $this-&gt;_id        = $id;
    $this-&gt;_data    = null;
}</programlisting>
      <para>Finally, we need a method to retrieve our data: getData()</para>

      <para>getData will check if the _data property has already been set. If
      it has, it will simply return it. Otherwise, it will load the data from
      the database.</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * Method to get a hello
 * @return object with data
 */

function &amp;getData()
{
    // Load the data
    if (empty( $this-&gt;_data )) {
        $query = ' SELECT * FROM #__hello '.
                '  WHERE id = '.$this-&gt;_id;
        $this-&gt;_db-&gt;setQuery( $query );
        $this-&gt;_data = $this-&gt;_db-&gt;loadObject();
    }
    if (!$this-&gt;_data) {
        $this-&gt;_data = new stdClass();
        $this-&gt;_data-&gt;id = 0;
        $this-&gt;_data-&gt;greeting = null;
    }
    return $this-&gt;_data;
}</programlisting>    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.form">
      <title>The Form</title>

      <para>Now all that is left is to create the form that the data will go
      into. Since we specified our layout as form, the form will go in a file
      in the tmpl directory of the hello view called form.php:</para>

      <programlisting xml:base="code/admin_views_hello_tmpl_form.php.xml">    &lt;?php defined('_JEXEC') or die('Restricted access'); ?&gt;

&lt;form action="index.php" method="post" name="adminForm" id="adminForm"&gt;
&lt;div class="col100"&gt;
    &lt;fieldset class="adminform"&gt;
        &lt;legend&gt;&lt;?php echo JText::_( 'Details' ); ?&gt;&lt;/legend&gt;
        &lt;table class="admintable"&gt;
        &lt;tr&gt;
            &lt;td width="100" align="right" class="key"&gt;
                &lt;label for="greeting"&gt;
                    &lt;?php echo JText::_( 'Greeting' ); ?&gt;:
                &lt;/label&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;td&gt;
                &lt;input class="text_area" type="text" name="greeting" id="greeting" size="32" maxlength="250" value="&lt;?php echo $this-&gt;hello-&gt;greeting;?&gt;" /&gt;
            &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;/fieldset&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="clr"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;input type="hidden" name="option" value="com_hello" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="id" value="&lt;?php echo $this-&gt;hello-&gt;id; ?&gt;" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="task" value="" /&gt;
&lt;input type="hidden" name="controller" value="hello" /&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;</programlisting>
      <para>Notice that in addition to the input field, there is a hidden
      field for the id. The user doesn't need to edit the id (and shouldn't),
      so we silently pass it along in the form.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality">
      <title>Implementing the Functionality</title>

      <para>So far, our controller only handles two tasks: edit and new.
      However, we also have buttons to save, delete and cancel records. We
      need to write code to handle and perform these tasks.</para>

      <sect3 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality.savingrecord">
        <title>Saving a Record</title>

        <para>The logical next step is to implement the functionality to save
        a record. Normally, this would require some switches and logic to
        handle various cases, such as the difference between creating a new
        record (an INSERT query), and updating an existing query (an UPDATE
        query). Also, there are complexities involved in getting the data from
        the form and putting it into the query.</para>

        <para>The Joomla! framework takes care of a lot of this for you. The
        JTable class makes it easy to manipulate records in the database
        without having to worry about writing the SQL code that lies behind
        these updates. It also makes it easy to transfer data from an HTML
        form into the database.</para>

        <sect4 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality.savingrecord.tableclass">
          <title>Creating the Table Class</title>

          <para>The JTable class is an abstract class from which you can
          derive child classes to work with specific tables. To use it, you
          simply create a class that extends the JTable class, add your
          database fields as properties, and override the constructor to
          specify the name of the table and the primary key.</para>

          <para>Here is our JTable class:</para>

          <programlisting xml:base="code/admin_tables_hello.php.xml">    &lt;?php
/**
 * Hello World table class
 * 
 * @package    Joomla.Tutorials
 * @subpackage Components
 * @link http://dev.joomla.org/component/option,com_jd-wiki/Itemid,31/id,tutorials:components/
 * @license        GNU/GPL
 */

// no direct access
defined('_JEXEC') or die('Restricted access');

/**
 * Hello Table class
 *
 * @package    Joomla.Tutorials
 * @subpackage Components
 */
class TableHello extends JTable
{
    /**
     * Primary Key
     *
     * @var int
     */
    var $id = null;

    /**
     * @var string
     */
    var $greeting = null;

    /**
     * Constructor
     *
     * @param object Database connector object
     */
    function TableHello(&gt; $db) {
        parent::__construct('#__hello', 'id', $db);
    }
}
?&gt;</programlisting>
          <para>You will see here that we have defined our two fields: the id
          field and the greeting field. Then we have defined a constructor,
          which will call the constructor of the parent class and pass it the
          name of the table (#__hello), the name of the field which is the
          primary key (id), and the database connector object.</para>

          <para>This file should be called hello.php and it will go in a
          directory called tables in the administrator section of our
          component.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality.savingrecord.modelfunction">
          <title>Implementing the Function in our Model</title>

          <para>We are now ready to add the method to the model which will
          save our record. We will call this method store. Our store() method
          will do three things: bind the data from the form to the TableHello
          object, check to ensure that the record is properly formed, and
          store the record in the database.</para>

          <para>Our method looks like:</para>

          <programlisting>/**
 * Method to store a record
 *
 * @access    public
 * @return    boolean    True on success
 */
function store()
{
    $row =&gt; $this-&gt;getTable();

    $data = JRequest::get( 'post' );
    // Bind the form fields to the hello table
    if (!$row-&gt;bind($data)) {
        $this-&gt;setError($this-&gt;_db-&gt;getErrorMsg());
        return false;
    }

    // Make sure the hello record is valid
    if (!$row-&gt;check()) {
        $this-&gt;setError($this-&gt;_db-&gt;getErrorMsg());
        return false;
    }

    // Store the web link table to the database
    if (!$row-&gt;store()) {
        $this-&gt;setError($this-&gt;_db-&gt;getErrorMsg());
        return false;
    }

    return true;
}</programlisting>
          <para>This method gets added to the hello model.</para>

          <para>The method takes one parameter, which is an associative array
          of data that we want to store in the database. This can easily be
          retrieved from the request as will be seen later.</para>

          <para>You will see that the first line retrieves a reference to our
          JTable object. If we name our table properly, we don't have to
          specify its name - the JModel class knows where to find it. You may
          recall that we called our table class TableHello and put it in a
          file called hello.php in the tables directory. If you follow this
          convention, the JModel class can create your object
          automatically.</para>

          <para>The second line will retrieve the data from the form. The
          JRequest class makes this very easy. In this case, we are retrieving
          all of the variables that were submitted using the 'POST' method.
          These will be returned as an associative array.</para>

          <para>The rest is easy - we bind, check and store. The bind() method
          will copy values from the array into the corresponding property of
          the table object. In this case, it will take the values of id and
          greeting and copy them to our TableHello object.</para>

          <para>The check() method will perform data verification. In the
          JTable() class, this method simply returns true. While this doesn't
          provide any value for us currently, by calling this method we make
          it possible to do data checking using our TableHello class in the
          future. This method can be overridden in our TableHello class with a
          method that performs the appropriate checks.</para>

          <para>The store() method will take the data that is in the object
          and store it in the database. If the id is 0, it will create a new
          record (INSERT), otherwise, it will update the existing record
          (UPDATE).</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality.savingrecord.addingtask">
          <title>Adding the Task to the Controller</title>

          <para>We are now ready to add our task to the controller. Since the
          task that we are firing is called 'save', we must call our method
          'save'. This is simple:</para>

          <programlisting>/**
 * save a record (and redirect to main page)
 * @return void
 */
function save()
{
    $model = $this-&gt;getModel('hello');

    if ($model-&gt;store()) {
        $msg = JText::_( 'Greeting Saved!' );
    } else {
        $msg = JText::_( 'Error Saving Greeting' );
    }

    // Check the table in so it can be edited.... we are done with it anyway
    $link = 'index.php?option=com_hello';
    $this-&gt;setRedirect($link, $msg);
}</programlisting>
          <para>All we do is get our model and invoke the store() method. Then
          we use the setRedirect() method to redirect back to our list of
          greetings. We also pass a message along, which will be displayed at
          the top of the page.</para>

          <figure id="mvctutorial4.message">
            <title>The message that was passed is displayed at the top of the
            page.</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/message.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality.deletingrecord">
      <title>Deleting a Record</title>

      <sect3 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality.deletingrecord.implementingmodelfunction">
        <title>Implementing the Function in the Model</title>

        <para>In the model, we will retrieve the list of IDs to delete and
        call the JTable class to delete them. Here it is:</para>

        <programlisting>/**
 * Method to delete record(s)
 *
 * @access    public
 * @return    boolean    True on success
 */
function delete()
{
    $cids = JRequest::getVar( 'cid', array(0), 'post', 'array' );
    $row =&gt; $this-&gt;getTable();

    foreach($cids as $cid) {
        if (!$row-&gt;delete( $cid )) {
            $this-&gt;setError( $row-&gt;getErrorMsg() );
            return false;
        }
    }                        

    return true;
}</programlisting>
        <para>We invoke the JRequest::getVar() method to get the data from the
        request, then we invoke the $row-&gt;delete() method to delete each
        row. By storing errors in the model we make it possible to retrieve
        them later if we so choose.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality.deletingrecord.removetask">
        <title>Handling the Remove Task in the Controller</title>

        <para>This is similar to the save() method which handled the save
        task:</para>

        <programlisting>/**
 * remove record(s)
 * @return void
 */
function remove()
{
    $model = $this-&gt;getModel('hello');
    if(!$model-&gt;delete()) {
        $msg = JText::_( 'Error: One or More Greetings Could not be Deleted' );
    } else {
        $msg = JText::_( 'Greeting(s) Deleted' );
    }

    $this-&gt;setRedirect( 'index.php?option=com_hello', $msg );
}</programlisting>      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvctutorial4.downanddirty.implementingfunctionality.canceloperation">
      <title>Cancelling the Edit Operation</title>

      <para>To cancel the edit operation, all we have to do is redirect back
      to the main view:</para>

      <programlisting>/**
 * cancel editing a record
 * @return void
 */
function cancel()
{
    $msg = JText::_( 'Operation Cancelled' );
    $this-&gt;setRedirect( 'index.php?option=com_hello', $msg );
}</programlisting>    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial4.conclusion">
    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>We have now implemented a basic backend to our component. We are now
    able to edit the entries that are viewed in the frontend. We have
    demonstrated the interaction between models, views and controllers. We
    have shown how the JTable class can be extended to provide easy access to
    tables in the database. It can also be seen how the JToolBarHelper class
    can be used to create button bars in components to present a standardized
    look between components.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial4.contributors">
    <title>Contributors</title>

    <simplelist>
      <member>staalanden</member>
    </simplelist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvctutorial4.download">
    <title>Download</title>

    <para>The component can be downloaded at: <ulink url="packages/com_hello4.zip">com_hello4.zip</ulink></para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
